Guide to the Margaret Brenman-Gibson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Margaret Brenman-Gibson Papers,
1940-1999
[Bulk Dates: 1963-1981]
Brenman-Gibson, Margaret.
18 linear ft. (18 record containers)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1635
6797567
Margaret Brenman-Gibson was a Harvard professor of Psychiatry. In 1981, she published a biography of American playwright Clifford Odets, entitled Clifford Odets - American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940. Brenman-Gibson and her husband, William Gibson, also a playwright, lived and worked in Stockbridge, Massachusetts. The collection consists of Brenman-Gibson's research files for her work on the Clifford Odets biography. It contains chronological notebooks, which outline each year of Odets' life, as well as correspondence, interviews, and interview transcripts with friends, relatives, and acquaintances of Odets. The collection also contains copies of correspondence, diaries, and notes from Odets. A small portion of the collection consists of personal correspondence between Brenman-Gibson, William Gibson, and Clifford Odets.
Biographical Note
Margaret Brenman-Gibson was a Harvard professor in the department of Psychiatry. In 1982, she became the first woman to be appointed as a full professor. Brenman-Gibson was the first non-physician from any discipline to receive full clinical as well as research psychoanalytic training in America. She is considered the first psychologist. Brenman-Gibson also had a deep interest in nuclear weapons and the use of nuclear power. She picketed and protested in numerous places, including Los Alamos. William Gibson, the husband of Margaret was an American playwright and novelist. The couple married in 1940. Shortly thereafter, Brenman-Gibson took a job as psychoanalyst at Stockbridge, Massachusetts and William published his book, The Cobweb, which was set in a psychiatric ward. In addition to her work on hypnosis and hypnotherapy, and her interest in nuclear weapons, she was also the biographer of American playwright Clifford Odets. Odets and the Gibson's were friends, as the correspondence between them reveals.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Margaret Brenman-Gibson's research files for her biography on American playwright, Clifford Odets, entitled Clifford Odets - American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940. Brenman-Gibson constructed detailed chronologies of Odets' life, taken from his various diaries, notes, and correspondence. These chronological notebooks form the basis for the collection. She also, in the course of her research, copied a good deal of Odets' personal papers: correspondence, diaries, notes, plays, and screenplays. The files she created when applying for grants while writing and researching the biography are represented in the collection. Additionally, Brenman-Gibson performed interviews with numerous friends, acquaintances, colleagues, and family members of Odets. Both her notes on the interviews and the tapes of the interviews can be found in the collection. Additionally, she corresponded with many of her interviewees, including Marlon Brando, Harold Clurman, Sammy Davis Jr., Elia Kazan, Lee and Paula Strasberg, and Luise Rainer. The correspondence in the collection primarily relates to the biography, and includes permission agreements. There is a small section of personal correspondence between Margaret and her husband William Gibson with Clifford Odets during the 1950s as well as with the Gibson's and Odets' son and daughter, Walt and Nora, after his death in 1963.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into three series:
Series I: Research Files for Clifford Odets - American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940
Subseries I.1: Chronological Notebooks
Subseries I.2: Correspondence, 1963-1989
Subseries I.3: Grants, 1957-1980
Subseries I.4: Interviews, 1963-1985
Sub-subseries I.4.A: Notes and Transcripts, 1963-1973
Sub-subseries I.4.B: Audio, 1963-1985
Subseries I.5: Clifford Odets Materials (copies of), 1940-1963
Subseries I.6: Original Worksheets, 1970-1975
Subseries I.7: Reference Files, 1950-1968
Subseries I.8: Research Files, 1961-1979
Subseries I.9: Rough Drafts, 1970-1975
Subseries I.10: Themes, 1959-1969
Subseries I.11: General Files, 1946-1999
Subseries I.12: Rolodex
Series II: Personal Correspondence, 1953-1993
Series III: Nuclear Weapons Activism, 1985-1987
Subjects
Group Theatre (U.S.); Brando, Marlon; Brenman-Gibson, Margaret; Clurman, Harold, 1901-1980; Davis, Sammy, 1925-1990; Gibson, William, 1914-2008; Odets, Clifford, 1906-1963; Odets, Walt; Rainer, Luise, 1910-; Strasberg, Lee; Dramatists, American--20th century--Biography; Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Notebooks; Research (document genres)
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least 2 business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
William Gibson Gift 2008 2008.2009.M008
William Gibson Gift 2011 2011.2012.M003
The Margaret Brenman-Gibson Papers were the gift of William Gibson in 2008. The donor agreement was signed by Montana Katz, who had power of attorney for Gibson. It came through the rare book dealer George Robert Minkoff. An addendum to the collection was donated in 2011.
Selected Related Material -- at Columbia
Clifford Odets Papers, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Research Files for Clifford Odets-American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940, 1940-1999
  Series I: Research Files consists of Brenman-Gibson's research files for her biography on the American playwright, Clifford Odets entitled, Clifford Odets - American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940. It contains chronological notebooks, which are basic summaries of Odets' life taken from his own diaries and correspondence, as well as interviews Brenman-Gibson conducted during the course of her research with Odets' family, friends, and acquaintances. Also found in Series I is the correspondence Brenman-Gibson had with various people related to Odets. Additionally, summaries, transcripts, and audio of the interviews are found in Series I. There are her files for grants in which she applied to conduct her research. There is significant material copied from Clifford Odets papers. This includes his diaries, correspondence, and notes. Rough drafts for Volume II of Brenman-Gibson's biography, which she never published, are also in Series I.
  - Subseries I.1: Chronological Notebooks
    Subseries I.1: Chronological Notebooks consists of the notebooks that Brenman-Gibson compiled during the course of writing her biography on Clifford Odets. The notebooks outline each year of Odets' life; the overviews provided by Odets' own original correspondence, diaries, and notes, but also from interviews Brenman-Gibson conducted with Odets' family, friends, and acquaintances. Odets' secretary, Virginia Rowe, worked with Brenman-Gibson during the course of her work on the biography. She provides her own recollections and summaries for each chronological notebook. The notebooks begin with an "early chronology", summarizing Odets' childhood, and then follow yearly from 1924-1963, the year Odets died. There are also notebooks entitled, "Aftermath", which trace the years following Odets' death.
    - Early Chronology, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1924, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1926, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1927, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1930s, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1941-1942, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1943-1945, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1944, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1945, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1947 July-December (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1947, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - 1948, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1949, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1950, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1951, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1951 Appendix (Box 3)
    - 1952, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1953, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1954, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1954-1955, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1956, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1957, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1958, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1959, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1960, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - 1961, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1962, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1962--Excerpts, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1963 January-June (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1963 July-December (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1963--Excerpts (Box 5)
    - 1964-1999--Aftermath (Box 5)
  - Subseries I.2: Correspondence, 1963-1989
    Subseries I.2: Correspondence contains the correspondence Brenman-Gibson had with people related to her work on the biography. Included here are letters from Odets' longtime friends and acquaintances: Stella Adler, Marlon Brando, Harold Clurman, Aaron Copland, Helen Deutsch, Alfred Hitchcock, Elia Kazan, Paula and Lee Strasburg, among numerous others. Much of the correspondence is carbon copies of Brenman-Gibson's outgoing letters, however, there are original letters from her correspondents. There is a section of the correspondence securing permissions to quote for her book from various people. The correspondence ranges in date from 1963-1989.
    - Master Address List, undated (Box 5)
    - A, 1964-1982 (Box 5)
    - Awake and Sing, 1970 (Box 5)
    - B, 1963-1968 (Box 5)
    - Brandt and Brandt, 1979 (Box 5)
    - C, 1964-1981 (Box 5)
    - Contract with Walt and Nora Odets, 1969-1979 (Box 5)
    - D, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
    - Dead End Letter, 1964-1969 (Box 5)
    - E, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
    - Editorial Work, 1976 (Box 5)
    - F, 1964-1979 (Box 5)
    - Flowering Peach, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Form Letters, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - G, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
    - Gollob, Herman, 1975-1981, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Greenbaum, Wolff and Ernst, 1969-1980 (Box 6)
    - H, 1964-1969 (Box 6)
    - Harris, Mark, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - Inquiries regarding Biography, 1968-1975 (Box 6)
    - J, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
    - Joan and Roberta, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - K, 1964-1982, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Knopf, Pat, 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Kobland, Herman, 1963-1981 (Box 6)
    - L, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
    - Lawson, John Howard, 1964-1978 (Box 6)
    - Legal, 1964-1974, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Libraries, 1967-1982 (Box 6)
    - M, 1963-1971 (Box 6)
    - Mc, 1966-1971 (Box 6)
    - N, 1965-1968 (Box 6)
    - New York Times, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
    - Permissions
      - 1965-1978 (Box 6)
      - A-D, 1978-1980 (Box 6)
      - E-K, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
      - L-R, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
      - Rainer, Luise, 1978-1980 (Box 6)
      - Rainer, Luise, 1964-1979 (Box 7)
      - S-Z, 1969-1979 (Box 7)
      - Signed Forms, 1978-1979 (Box 7)
      - Permissions for Photos, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Rowe, Virginia
      - 1963-1966 (Box 7)
      - Contract, 1963-1978 (Box 7)
    - General, 1968-1989, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Subseries I.3: Grants, 1957-1980
    Subseries I.3: Grants contains the files that Brenman-Gibson kept which document her application for grant funds to conduct her research on the Clifford Odets' biography. There are application materials for such funds as American Association of University Women, the Guggenheim Foundation, the National Endowment for the Humanities, and the National Institute for Mental Health. The grant files range in date from 1957-1980.
    - American Association of University Women, 1972-1980 (Box 7)
    - Foundation Fund for Research in Psychiatry, 1967-1979 (Box 7)
    - Foundation for Research in Psychoanalysis, 1967-1976 (Box 7)
    - The Grant Foundation, 1971-1976 (Box 7)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1968-1976 (Box 7)
    - Lederer Foundation, 1964-1978 (Box 7)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities
      - 1968-1976, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - Matching Grant, 1971 (Box 7)
    - National Institute for Mental Health
      - 1965-1968 (Box 7)
      - Research Science Award, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Public Health Service, undated (Box 7)
    - The Rockefeller Foundation (includes recommendation from Norman Mailer), 1973-1976 (Box 7)
    - Sharcar, Inc., 1971 (Box 7)
    - Variable Floating Research Fund, 1966-1976 (Box 7)
    - William C. Whitney Foundation, 1968-1976 (Box 7)
    - Application for Research Funds, 1972-1974, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 8)
    - Budgets, 1957-1974 (Box 8)
    - Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 8)
    - Fund-raising
      - Creativity Research, 1963-1970, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Rejections, 1968-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Questionnaires, 1964-1974, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Recommendations, 1964-1980, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Ideas, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Research Funds--Foundations, 1967-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Subseries I.4: Interviews, 1963-1985
    Subseries I.4: Interviews contains the summaries, transcripts, and audio of interviews Brenman-Gibson conducted while researching for her biography on Clifford Odets.
    - Sub-subseries I.4.A: Notes and Transcripts, 1963-1973
      Sub-subseries I.4.A: Notes and Transcripts consists of notes and transcripts to interviews that Brenman-Gibson conducted in the course of research her biography on Clifford Odets.
      - Adler, Jay 1965 June 18 (Box 8)
      - Alden, Hortense, 1967 February 21 (Box 8)
      - Aronson, Boris, 1965 April 19 (Box 8)
      - Bard, Ben, 1965 June 21 (Box 8)
      - Brando, Marlon, 1965 June 21 (Box 8)
      - Braun, Hannah, 1965 June 24 (Box 8)
      - Burger, Mary, 1965 June 19 (Box 8)
      - Clurman, Harold, 1964 October 16, 1966 July 24 (Box 8)
      - Clurman, Bob, 1965 September 8 (Box 8)
      - Corcoran, Catherine, 1965 June 27 (Box 8)
      - Curtis, Tony, 1965 June 25 (Box 8)
      - Dunne, Philip, 1966 March 31 (Box 8)
      - Elkins, Hillard, 1964 October 18 (Box 8)
      - Erikson, Leif, 1965 June 21 (Box 8)
      - Gertsman, Jack, 1965 June 22 (Box 8)
      - Gibson, William
        - 1963, (4 folders) (Box 8)
        - Notes, 1963 (Box 8)
        - Notes, 1963, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Goetz, Mr. and Mrs. Wm, 1965 June 18 (Box 9)
      - Gordon, Clark and McVeagh, Eve, 1966 April 2 (Box 9)
      - Harris, Hillary, 1967 May 25 (Box 9)
      - Herman, Harvey, 1965 June 26 (Box 9)
      - Heilpern, Mr. and Mrs. Carl K., 1966 February 3 (Box 9)
      - Hiss, Alger, 1965 July 4 (Box 9)
      - HUAC, undated (Box 9)
      - Kabaker, Florence Odets, 1965 June 20 (Box 9)
      - Karlen, Stymean, 1965 June 10 (Box 9)
      - Karzmar, Leonard, 1965 June 24 (Box 9)
      - Kaye, Sidney, 1965 May 26 (Box 9)
      - Krim, Arthur, 1967 January 31 (Box 9)
      - Lancaster, Burt, 1965 June 21 (Box 9)
      - Lane, Mrs. Burton, 1966 March 17 (Box 9)
      - Lawson, John Howard, 1965 June 19 (Box 9)
      - Leof, Milton, 1966 April 7 (Box 9)
      - Levy, Genevieve, 1964 May 20 (Box 9)
      - Lipper, Milton and Frances, 1965 April 20 (Box 9)
      - Mason, Josephine, 1965 June 27 (Box 9)
      - Meisner, Sandy, 1965 April 30 (Box 9)
      - Norton, E., 1967 June 25 (Box 9)
      - Odets, L.J., 1965 May 4 (Box 9)
      - Penn, Arthur, 1965 June 21 (Box 9)
      - Rainer, Luise, 1964 March21 (Box 9)
      - Ray, Nicholas, 1966 July 25 (Box 9)
      - Renoir, Jean and Dido, 1966 June 25 (Box 9)
      - Robinson, Edward G, 1965 June 25 (Box 9)
      - Rosenberg, Jerry, 1967 February 2 (Box 9)
      - Ross, Madi Leof, 1966 April 1 (Box 9)
      - Rossman, Fredda, 1964 January 12 (Box 9)
      - Rowe, Virginia, 1963 (Box 9)
      - Saarinen, Aline, 1964 April 7 (Box 9)
      - Selznick, Irene Mayer, 1966 June 27 (Box 9)
      - Shulman, Morris, 1967 February 7 (Box 9)
      - Smith, Bernard, 1965 June 25 (Box 9)
      - Stell, Gladys, 1965 June 22 (Box 9)
      - Strasberg, Lee, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
      - Tone, Franchot, 1966 June 27 (Box 9)
      - United Bank Discussion, 1965 August 23 (Box 9)
      - Voutsinas, Andreas, 1966 July 6 (Box 9)
      - Summaries
        - A, 1964-1968 (Box 9)
        - B, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
        - C, 1964-1973 (Box 9)
        - Clurman, Harold, 1963-1969, (2 folders) (Box 9)
        - Compton, Juleen, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
        - D, 1964-1967 (Box 9)
        - E, 1964-1968 (Box 9)
        - F, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
        - G, 1964-1967 (Box 9)
        - H, 1964-1967 (Box 9)
        - I, 1964 (Box 9)
        - J, undated (Box 9)
        - K, 1964-1968 (Box 9)
        - Kazan, Elia, 1964 (Box 9)
        - L, 1963-1967 (Box 9)
        - M, 1964-1973 (Box 9)
        - N, 1967 (Box 9)
        - O, 1964-1965, (2 folders) (Box 9)
        - P, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
        - R, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
        - R, 1963-1967 (Box 10)
        - S, 1963-1967 (Box 10)
        - Strasberg, Lee and Paula, 1963-1968 (Box 10)
        - T, 1965-1968 (Box 10)
        - U, 1965 (Box 10)
        - W, 1964-1966 (Box 10)
        - XYZ, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Sub-subseries I.4.B: Audio, 1963-1985
      Sub-subseries I.4.B: Audio consists of the audiocassettes and reel-to-reel tapes of interviews Brenman-Gibson conducted while writing her biography on Clifford Odets.
      - Audiocassettes and Reel-to-Reel Tapes, 1963-1985 (Box 17)
  - Subseries I.5: Clifford Odets Materials (copies of), 1940-1963
    Subseries I.5: Clifford Odets Materials (copies of) contains copied material from Odets' original papers. Found here are copies of Odets' correspondence from 1961-1963, copies of his appointment books and diaries from 1940-1963, as well as notes he wrote for various productions, including: Mafia Man, North Star, Only the Young, Strange Hunt, and Two Agents.
    - Appointment Books
      - 1953, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1954 (Box 10)
      - 1955 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence
      - 1961 January-April (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1961 May-July (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1961 August-September (Box 10)
      - 1961 October-December (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1962 January-February (Box 10)
      - 1962 March-May (Box 10)
      - 1962 June-August (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1962 September-December (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - 1963 January-February (Box 10)
      - 1963 March-April (Box 10)
      - 1963 May-July (Box 11)
      - 1963 August (Box 11)
    - Diaries
      - 1940, (4 folders) (Box 11)
      - 1958 (Box 11)
      - 1961 (Box 11)
      - 1962 (pages taken from front) (Box 11)
      - 1963 (Box 11)
    - Mafia Man--Draft, 1963 March (Box 11)
    - Monroe, Marilyn--Correspondence, Notes, Drafts, and other Materials, 1959 undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - North Star--Draft, 1963 March 12 (Box 11)
    - Notes
      - 1961, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - 1962-1963, (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - 1963 (Box 11)
      - 1963 (from hospital) (Box 11)
      - undated (typed by Margaret Brenman-Gibson) (Box 11)
      - undated (on his diary), (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Only the Young--Notes and Correspondence, 1963 April (Box 11)
    - Strange Hunt--Notes and Correspondence, 1963 (Box 11)
    - TV Story Ideas, 1963 undated (Box 11)
    - Two Agents--Notes, undated (Box 11)
  - Subseries I.6: Original Worksheets, 1970-1975
    Subseries I.6: Original Worksheets consists of handwritten notes by Brenman-Gibson taken during the course of her work on the Odets' biography. These worksheets range in date from 1970-1975.
    - 1970, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1970, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1971-1972, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1974-1975, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Subseries I.7: Reference Files, 1950-1968
    Subseries I.7: Reference Files is a general filing system Brenman-Gibson kept, which contains articles and notes on art, artists, creativity, and the theater.
    - General, 1950-1968, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - C, 1964 (Box 12)
    - D, 1954-1964 (Box 12)
    - E, 1961, 1964 (Box 12)
    - F, 1963 (Box 12)
    - G, 1957-1966 (Box 12)
    - H, 1960-1963 (Box 12)
    - K, 1956-1965 (Box 12)
    - M, 1955-1965 (Box 12)
    - P, 1958-1964 (Box 12)
    - R, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - S, 1959-1966 (Box 12)
    - T, 1961-1964 (Box 12)
    - W, 1961-1964 (Box 12)
  - Subseries I.8: Research Files, 1961-1979
    Subseries I.8: Research Files are files of notes that Brenman-Gibson kept on each of Odets' plays, screenplays, and television shows.
    - General, 1961-1965 (Box 12)
    - References regarding Clifford Odets' Plays, undated (Box 12)
    - The Actor, 1961-1964 undated (Box 12)
    - An Old Fashioned Man, undated (Box 12)
    - Awake and Sing, 1964-1979 (Box 12)
    - The Big Knife, 1965 1968 undated (Box 12)
    - Clash by Night, 1965-1971 undated (Box 12)
    - The Country Girl, 1964-1972 undated (Box 12)
    - Cuban Play, 1964 (Box 12)
    - Dark Companion, 1964 (Box 12)
    - The Flowering Peach, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - Golden Boy, 1964-1966 undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - I Can't Sleep, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - I Heard the Music Start, undated (Box 12)
    - Mother and Son, 1956-1961 (Box 12)
    - Night Music, 1964-1965 undated (Box 12)
    - Paradise Lost, 1964-1969 undated (Box 12)
    - Private Treaty, undated (Box 12)
    - Projected Plays, 1965, undated (Box 12)
    - Rocket to the Moon, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - The Russian People, undated (Box 12)
    - Silent Partner, 1964-1968 undated (Box 12)
    - Tides of Fundy, 1964-1966 (Box 12)
    - Till the Day I Die, 1964-1968 undated (Box 12)
    - Waiting for Lefty, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - Movies
      - Deadline at Dawn, 1964 (Box 12)
      - The General Died at Dawn, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
      - Humoresque, undated (Box 12)
      - Joseph and His Brethren, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
      - None but the Lonely Heart, undated (Box 12)
      - Rhapsody in Blue, undated (Box 12)
      - Wild in the Country, 1967 (Box 12)
    - Television, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - Unfinished Plays, 1964-1966 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
    - Notes for Full-Length Plays, undated (Box 12)
    - Notes for Movies, undated (Box 12)
  - Subseries I.9: Rough Drafts, 1970-1975
    Subseries I.9: Rough Drafts contains early drafts of Volume II of Brenman-Gibson's biography on Clifford Odets. The drafts cover the years 1940-1944.
    - 1940 January-Spring, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1940 Summer-December (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1940 Summer-1941 December (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1942-1943, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1944- (Box 13)
    - 1940 January-Spring (Chapter 24), 1970 (Box 16)
    - 1940 Summer-December (Chapter 24), 1970-1971, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1941 January -December (Chapter 26), 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - 1942-1943 (Chapter 27), 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1944-, 1974-1975 (Box 16)
  - Subseries I.10: Themes, 1959-1969
    Subseries I.10: Themes is a section of research files that Brenman-Gibson kept, which document her developing ideas on themes for the Clifford Odets biography. She delves into ideas such as creativity, psychoanalysis, sex, and relations that Odets' had with men, women, and his family and children.
    - General Comments and Prefatory Statements, 1964 (Box 13)
    - Abandonment
      - 1965 (Box 13)
      - Orality, 1965-1966 (Box 13)
      - Music, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - Activity/Passivity, undated (Box 13)
    - Aggression
      - undated (Box 13)
      - Masochism, 1964 (Box 13)
    - Art/Creativity
      - Odets, Clifford, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Brenman-Gibson, Margaret, 1964-1967 (Box 13)
      - Gibson, William, 1959-1969 (Box 13)
      - Others, 1962-1968 (Box 13)
      - Identification with Beethoven, 1964, undated (Box 13)
      - Identification with O'Neill, undated (Box 13)
      - Identification with Mozart, 1965 (Box 13)
      - Identification with Whitman, undated (Box 13)
    - Artist in America, 1963-1965 undated (Box 13)
    - Belonging/Acceptance, 1963, undated (Box 13)
    - Death, 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - Giving and Getting, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - Family